There are twelve of them.
twelve stadiums built in the four corners of Europe,
imagined by the most daring architects and built by thousands of workers and engineers.
Twelve gigantic arenas,
Selected to host matches for a global event,
the 2020 European Football Championship.
Embarking on a unique tour of Europe,
Discovering the most beautiful stadiums on the continent.
In this episode,
the match will pit.
The Gazprom Arena in Saint Petersburg, Russia, to the Olympic Stadium in Baku, Azerbaijan.
On one hand,
an arena resembling a flying saucer,
whose construction required more than 10 years of work,
equipped with a retractable roof and a removable lawn,
and which is home to one of the biggest clubs in Europe,
Zenit Saint Petersburg.
This stadium is truly fantastic.
And the acoustics are so impressive.
Me,
when I step onto the lawn,
I feel a bit like I'm in a huge theatre.
On the other hand,
a venue that has already hosted the biggest European finals.
With architecture inspired by a 12th-century tower,
capable of withstanding the strongest winds and earthquakes,
and which was built in barely two years.
The Baku Olympic Stadium is the largest stadium in the Caucasus region.
A venue with a capacity of 68,000 people.
Given the number of components to be manufactured,
Meeting construction deadlines was our biggest challenge.
A head-to-head between two stadiums,
located at the crossroads between Europe and Asia,
and which are among the most modern speakers in the world.
Let us begin our journey on the shores of the Gulf of the Baltic Sea, where the city of Saint Petersburg stands.
Nicknamed the Venice of the North,
The city was founded in 1703 on the marshy mouth of the Neva River.
Today,
with its 5 million inhabitants,
It has become the second largest city in Russia after Moscow.
The city previously had two stadiums.
The first,
Petrovsky Stadium,
located on the island of the same name.
An old stadium with a capacity of 22,000,
built in 1925,
which hosted FC Zenit Saint Petersburg matches for several decades.
The other one,
Kirov Stadium,
located less than 4 km away,
on another island of barely more than 3 km²,
surrounded by the arms of the Neva.
Krestovski Island.
Inaugurated in 1950,
The stadium could accommodate up to 110,000 people.
It is on the site of the old Kirov stadium that the authorities have decided to build an ultra-modern stadium for the city's club to play in.
It was named the Gazprom Arena.
The enclosure came straight from the imagination of the Japanese architect.
Kisho Kurokawa,
now deceased,
but considered one of the greatest architects in the world.
Among his achievements,
among his most notable achievements,
the Nakagin capsule tower,
the Tokyo National Arts Center,
but above all,
Oita Stadium,
built for the 2002 FIFA World Cup.
Featuring the largest retractable roof in the country,
This arena with its exceptional design has been nicknamed the Big Eye.
Even back then,
Kisho Kurokawa had proven to the world his originality and his ability to do things.
It drew inspiration from the most unexpected models.
And the shape of the Gazprom Arena in Saint Petersburg is further proof of the architect's inventiveness.
His vision was to give the stadium the appearance of a flying saucer.
The shape of the stadium,
the roof,
the windows,
the stairs,
Everything has been designed so that the enclosure resembles an extraterrestrial UFO point by point.
Yuji Imayo was part of the team that designed this stadium under the direction of Kisho Kurokawa.
First of all,
This stadium has a circular shape.
whereas usually,
Football stadiums are usually elliptical or rectangular in shape.
This time,
Kurokawa gave the enclosure the shape of a stadium.
This is the main reason that gives it this spaceship-like appearance.
And then,
There are also these very special windows.
I remember Kurokawa repeatedly making me correct my plans, pointing out that I probably hadn't done that.
Probably never seen a UFO window.
And finally,
There are stairs.
Today,
They are fixed.
but initially,
We wanted them to be retractable.
A bit like when a UFO hatch opens to let the crew out.
The day after the presentation of our project,
We could read on the front page of the city's newspapers that a UFO was going to land in Saint Petersburg.
We hadn't yet told anyone that we had used a spaceship as our model.
It was hoped that people would discover it for themselves.
And that was the case.
So it was a great victory for us.
I think that where he is,
Kurokawa is watching us from his spaceship and he is really very happy.
And I think he thanks everyone from the bottom of his heart.
While a perfectly circular stadium was extremely rare at the time,
There's another one that's recently appeared.
Located 3000 km southeast of Saint Petersburg,
in a country located between Europe and Asia,
Azerbaijan.
It's in Baku,
capital city of 2 million inhabitants,
which was inaugurated in 2015,
in the heart of the city's new districts,
the Olympic stadium.
This uniquely designed venue has become one of the country's new architectural prides.
The stadium was designed by the architects at ERIM.
a prestigious South Korean firm.
Their objective?
To rediscover in this new building the traces of the country's glorious past and the symbols of the city.
Because Baku,
located on the shores of the Caspian Sea,
was previously known primarily for its medieval city,
its ramparts,
its minarets and its magnificent palaces.
When this stadium was designed,
which is the largest stadium in Azerbaijan,
We first had to decide what it could look like.
He was supposed to represent the country,
So we asked ourselves what element should serve as our inspiration.
The main source of inspiration for architects,
It's her.
Maiden Tower,
known as the Virgin's Tower.
Built in the 12th century and standing about thirty meters tall,
The building, a UNESCO World Heritage Site, has now become one of the city's emblems, known throughout the world.
The stadium was therefore designed to resemble the Maiden Tower.
in a perfectly cylindrical shape.
The facade was then designed in the same spirit as that of the 12th-century tower.
whose walls are composed of a succession of projecting grey limestone stones,
alternating with recessed gypsum plaster.
A structure that gives the impression that the tower is composed of black and white stripes.
So it was this same principle that was reproduced on the stadium.
But instead of preserving the rectangular shape of the bricks,
This time the architects opted for diamond-shaped panels.
The diamond motif is also a symbol of fire.
And since Azerbaijan is known as the land of fire,
We thought we could bring together the two great symbols of the country with the stadium.
The first,
It is the symbol of fire.
It is the facade that recalls the succession of bricks of the Maiden Tower and the second,
the symbol of fire which represents the country.
Public access to the stadium was designed with reference to another emblem of Azerbaijan,
the Cannes palace.
Located in the north of the country,
300 km from Baku,
This palace was the summer residence of the Kans.
rulers of the former feudal state of the Caucasus in the 18th century.
Renowned worldwide for the colours of its façades and its stained glass windows,
It features windows known as shabaka windows.
made of fragments of glass and wood,
assembled without glue or nails.
It was their motif that inspired the architects to design the arrival at the stadium.
The three access ramps leading to the central enclosure are like three wooden axes that cross the circle of glass in the stained-glass windows of the Palais des Cannes.
The Baku stadium, like that of Saint Petersburg, is therefore among the rare perfectly circular venues, and their original design makes them unique structures in the world.
But one of them has something special that the other does not.
The Gazprom Arena has a retractable roof, the design of which required several years of work.
Because in the heart of the Venice of the North,
this exceptional city,
A stadium was needed that could withstand the extreme conditions of the Far North.
Here,
in winter,
Temperatures regularly fall below minus 20 degrees and snow and wind are omnipresent.
The stadium was therefore equipped with a retractable roof,
a transparent dome 150 meters in diameter which allows the venue to be used regardless of the weather.
Nicolas Yegorenko is the stadium's technical director.
He takes us inside the very structure of the roof,
where the opening system for this giant dome is located.
Here,
we are at the highest point,
just under the retractable roof which actually consists of two parts.
Today,
We opened the roof for the first time since the end of the long winter period.
There,
We are in the testing phase to verify that everything works perfectly.
It takes between 20 and 40 minutes for the roof to open completely.
The dome is composed of four distinct parts.
Two that remain fixed and two others that can slide on rails propelled by electric trolleys.
In total,
28 trolleys are needed to open and close the two moving parts of the roof.
An ingenious system that allows you to preserve,
regardless of the weather conditions outside,
a temperature of 15 degrees inside the enclosure.
The temperature in the stadium is maintained using the same principle as that of major airports.
A ventilation system sends warm air inside and helps to maintain a constant temperature.
The dome was also specially designed to support the weight of snow in winter and prevent it from accumulating on the roof.
It is made of a thermoplastic material called ETFE.
Lighter and much cheaper than glass,
but extremely durable.
And very often used in the construction of megastadiums.
The dome is a
A kind of transparent membrane.
The moving part is composed of two separate layers that form a chamber which is pressurized.
The machines inject compressed air inside and the roof is thus inflated a bit like a balloon.
In addition to that,
The spherical shape of the roof makes it even more difficult for snow to accumulate on the dome in winter because the wind makes it slide off the flat surface.
And if on certain parts of the roof,
It does accumulate a little in all cases.
The cases,
It will eventually melt.
Because the hot air inside the enclosure tends to rise,
He will arrive under the dome.
Since the dome is not insulated,
The warm air will heat it and melt the snow.
But this retractable roof system forced architects and engineers to innovate,
because this area of ​​71,000 m² is a heavy burden.
Very heavy.
15,000 tonnes for the circular roof and its transparent dome.
26,000 for the metal structure on which it rests.
The equivalent of the weight of 4 Eiffel Towers.
To support the whole thing,
It was impossible to use interior pillars that would obstruct the spectators' view.
The designers therefore used techniques usually employed for the construction of water bridges.
They installed it on top of the pool,
At the top of the stadium,
8 pylons that pass through the roof and are anchored to the ground.
At their summit,
Each one of them is equipped with tensioned cables that allow it to absorb part of the load.
In addition to this system
2 enormous metal beams and 4 mega-pillars made of reinforced concrete onto which part of the load is transferred.
Inside the stadium,
The two mega-beams located just below the retractable roof can be easily identified.
We can also see the eight pylons that pass through the top of the stands to anchor themselves to the ground.
But neither the megabeams,
nor do the pylons obstruct the spectators' view.
even those who are watching the match from the top of the stands.
The idea of ​​these eight pylons, which function like guy wires, did not come from nowhere.
The architect Kurokawa had already used a similar system for one of his previous buildings,
the Toyota Stadium.
It is indeed the same system as the one used for the Toyota Stadium near Nagoya.
But this one only has 4 pylons,
whereas the one in Saint Petersburg has 8.
Technically...
It would have been simpler to manufacture them with an external orientation.
But Kurokawa wanted the masts to point towards the sky.
The local engineers asked us several times to turn them outwards instead.
But we refused.
And it's thanks to that that we were able to achieve this aesthetic in the end.
Thanks to this architectural feat,
The roof and the rest of the building appear to be disconnected from each other.
The roof thus appears to almost float in the air.
offering a further similarity to the flying saucer envisioned by the architect.
If in Saint Petersburg,
The workers and engineers had to find solutions to bring the Japanese architect's imagination to life.
In Baku,
the manufacturers had to cope,
them,
to other challenges.
The most complex,
to ensure the stability of the building.
First problem,
The site chosen by the authorities to build the stadium is located on the shores of Lake Boyuxor.
The location has the advantage of being situated between the international airport and the city center.
It is therefore easily accessible for residents and for spectators from all over the world.
The construction of the enclosure is part of a vast project to rehabilitate the lake and its surroundings.
long exploited by the mining and oil industry.
To such an extent that it seemed almost impossible to build on this coating.
We appreciate a stadium of such importance.
The area where the stadium is located was really difficult,
especially in terms of soil quality,
because until now, people came there to extract oil.
You could almost say that we are on the lake and that the stadium is built on very unstable ground.
This was one of the biggest challenges for the construction.
Designing the foundations required a great deal of inventiveness.
In addition to its proximity to the lake and the poor soil quality,
The location is in an area subject to very strong winds.
Worse,
It is even classified as a seismic zone.
In the event of an earthquake,
Seismic waves can generate forces known as uplift forces.
In other words,
The stadium could simply be ripped from the ground by the force of the earthquake.
To ensure that the enclosure can withstand the stress,
The engineers opted for a particular foundation system generally used for high-rise buildings.
They were sunk into the ground just below the stadium using concrete piles reinforced with metal rods.
Typically for this type of construction,
Three or four piles are sufficient to guarantee the stability of the structure.
But in this case,
They decided to pull out all the stops.
To avoid any structural problems,
2500 reinforced concrete piles were installed before the construction of the enclosure.
800 under the access ramps and the esplanade and
1700 under the sand.
the stadium itself.
These piles are 1.20 m in diameter.
They descend to a depth of 35 m and their summit is located just at ground level.
Once the 2500 piles are completed,
The area on which the stadium was to be built was covered with several layers up to a thickness of 3 m.
Gravel first,
then a first layer of concrete.
Next comes a plastic film for insulation.
Then a waterproofing fabric called geotextile.
And finally, a last layer of reinforced concrete to cover everything.
To finish,
The building was constructed around a superstructure composed of 60 mega-pillars of concrete.
A design that allows the Baku Olympic Stadium to withstand winds and earthquakes.
But the engineers faced another challenge.
The stadium was scheduled to be inaugurated in 2015 for the first European Games.
And the work could not begin until 2013.
It took barely more than two years to build such a structure,
The challenge was immense.
The deadlines were very short.
We had to plan all the activities at the same time.
Everything that mattered,
It was about delivering on time.
We needed to use all our resources in the most efficient way possible.
including labor,
the manufacturing of the components or the design.
Construction began with 8 million cubic meters of backfilling and excavation.
Afterwards,
The concrete has been poured.
360,000 m3 of concrete were poured on the site.
To meet the deadlines,
The construction site was divided into 8 identical zones, allowing several teams to work at the same time and to accelerate the pace of work.
The components of the metal structure were prefabricated in a factory in Türkiye.
In order to speed things up,
55,000 tonnes of steel structures were manufactured in a factory in Türkiye.
shipped to Baku and installed on site.
The metal framework was then assembled on site by 600 welders.
A considerable amount of material had to be transported to the site.
Building within such tight deadlines was truly our biggest challenge.
Around each area of ​​the construction site,
as the concrete bleachers began to take shape,
The metal sub-parts were assembled one by one,
ready to be positioned on the building.
First, the vertical elements,
placed along the 60 mega-pillars of concrete.
Then,
the structural elements,
to form the roof.
Each piece was hoisted using mega-cranes capable of transporting more than 1200 tons of metal.
Each element of the framework was then fixed to the top of the mega-pillars of concrete,
then connected with the element located right next to it.
A perfectly controlled organization which made it possible to complete the 28,000 m² of roof in exactly 210 days.
The perimeter of the enclosure and the roof were then covered with an outer layer of ETFE.
the same material as that used for the dome of the roof of Saint Petersburg which lets light into the stadium.
The facade is designed with two layers of TFE.
inside which LED lighting has been installed.
The facade thus becomes a gigantic screen.
In total,
We managed to cover 28,000 m² of roof and 36,000 m² of facade in 24 months.
By working 7 days a week and 24 hours a day,
and above all by scrupulously respecting the schedule planned from the outset,
We managed to build the stadium without changing the delivery date.
And we finished on time.
The Baku Olympic Stadium, with its 68,000 seats, was inaugurated on March 6, 2015.
that is, three months before the start of the European Games.
The whole world watched the opening ceremony of the European Games in the Batum Olympic Stadium.
More than 200 television channels broadcast the event.
And we,
That's for sure.
We were extremely proud of the comments we received from all countries regarding the quality of the stadium.
In my opinion,
It's a truly magnificent speaker.
And it was built to a very high standard of quality.
It is clear that in the future,
Many other major sporting events will be able to be organized here.
You know,
We visited many stadiums in Europe before starting construction.
And ours truly stands out thanks to its unique design.
which is reminiscent of the city's construction.
The flame and the fire.
And for us,
It is very important that this stadium represents these symbols of our history.
An exceptional stadium,
exceptional project.
If in Baku,
It lasted barely 26 months.
in Saint Petersburg,
the construction of the stadium,
She,
required a lot.
much more time.
In total,
It took 11 years of work to build the Gazprom Arena.
The cost of the project would exceed one billion euros.
making the Saint Petersburg stadium one of the most expensive in history.
Among the most amazing innovations found in this exceptional arena,
One of them concerns one of the most important elements of a football stadium,
his land.
The entire 120-meter long by 80-meter wide pitch can be moved out of the enclosure and positioned on an outdoor space built to the exact dimensions of the pitch.
An extremely complex maneuver that requires two days of preparation and that the stadium team only performs on very rare occasions.
Since our stadium has a retractable roof,
We don't move the field often.
This only applies when we organize events that are not sporting events.
concerts or other events,
where it is necessary to bring a large audience onto the field.
In that case,
We cannot allow people onto the lawn.
Otherwise they risk being damaged.
Therefore, it is to preserve it that the field is moved outside.
The ground moves thanks to a system composed of several traction modules that allow the enormous 6000-tonne structure to advance.
Each module consists of two drive wheels on tires with a diameter of 1 meter that move at a speed of 5 cm per second.
All modules are equipped with an electric motor and they are all synchronized to ensure the smoothest possible movement.
In total,
There are 16 modules at the front and 16 at the rear.
But moving such a structure induces significant stresses at the points of contact between the wheels and the ground.
Again,
It required some ingenuity.
To reduce the weight on the wheels,
The engineers designed an air cushion system.
When ground movement begins,
The cushion is triggered, which lifts the ground and reduces the weight on the wheels.
This reduces wear on the wheels and allows the terrain to be moved without fear of damaging the structure.
This air cushion system is composed of 36 injection modules.
They are installed at the front and rear of the field and are equipped with high-pressure fans.
The fans allow 22 m3 of air per second to be injected into a sealed cavity located under the lawn and which occupies the entire perimeter of the field.
In 30 minutes,
the cavity is filled and makes it possible to almost completely compensate for the weight supported by the drive wheels of the traction modules.
Thanks to sensors located around the structure,
A centralized control system helps maintain uniform pressure in the cavity throughout the entire displacement process.
The whole assembly can then slide effortlessly,
but at a very slow speed
outwards.
And it takes an average of 4 hours for the terrain to reach its location.
One of the most critical aspects of this extraordinary setup is the 80-meter-wide empty space created at the end of the field to allow the passage of the grass.
Above rests the weight of the bleachers without any pillar being able to support the load.
This is a truly unique part of the stadium.
Actually,
It's a bit like we're under a bridge made of reinforced concrete that has to support a very heavy load.
Just above us is the fan zone.
And of course,
The fans are constantly jumping and moving around.
That is why we have installed a monitoring system that measures the deformation of this structure during the match.
The case of this stand at the Gazprom Arena shows how much the structures of modern mega-stadiums must withstand the strongest stresses.
In Baku,
given the risk of earthquakes in the region,
The venue was even equipped with a state-of-the-art earthquake detection system.
The last major earthquake struck Azerbaijan on November 25, 2000.
With a magnitude of 6.8 on the Richter scale,
Its epicenter was located near the coasts of the Caspian Sea.
just 25 km southeast of Baku city centre.
The fire caused the deaths of around thirty people and damage to more than 90 buildings in the city.
The authorities therefore preferred not to take any risks during the construction of the stadium.
Seismic wave sensors have therefore been installed all around the stadium to detect the slightest tremor and immediately send the information to the control center located inside the stadium.
This is what we call our magic box.
Actually,
This is the seismic warning system.
This system allows information to be received in less than 8 seconds.
So if the epicenter of the earthquake is located 120 km from the stadium,
The information will be transmitted to this box in just 24 seconds.
So it only takes 24 seconds to...
so that the alarm sounds throughout the stadium and the device triggers a general shutdown of the venue.
The backup generators then kick in and all electrical systems are switched over to the generators.
Gas,
him too.
is cut off.
It is in this ultra-secure space that all the stadium's systems are managed.
Heating,
lighting,
Video surveillance or even lawn irrigation.
Welcome to a fully connected stadium.
a football 3.0 stadium.
Since its inauguration in 2015,
This ultra-modern venue has become the symbol of a new Azerbaijan.
open to the world and to the future.
Inside,
Every detail has been considered to ensure that the Baku Olympic Stadium impresses visitors from all over the world.
The interior of the stadium has been designed to create a very comfortable atmosphere.
with clean lines.
The atmosphere is very bright and the colours are very pleasant.
The decor blends ancient and modern influences.
a bit like the stadium itself.
Actually,
Every single element of the stadium reflects this philosophy.
Our stadium is not only the official home of the national football team,
but it is also a multifunctional center where we can host different types of events.
It can range from small events like parties or birthdays.
up to major international events.
And of course,
We are very proud to show everyone the quality of our facilities and the services we can offer our visitors.
whether they are VIPs,
fans,
journalists,
players and, of course, athletes.
The stadium has a capacity of 68,700 seats.
which makes our stadium the largest in the region.
We have 126 VIP suites and 6 tiers of grandstand seating available for everyone.
The stadiums in Baku and Saint Petersburg are therefore two perfect examples of what stadiums of the future should become.
Forget the old sports arena of the past where only the pitch and the stands mattered.
Today,
A stadium must be able to accommodate the public in the best possible conditions of comfort.
Yuri Fedotov,
the head of security at the Gazprom Arena,
takes us to one of the most secret places within the compound,
Access to the stands is prohibited for spectators.
We are in what is called the presidential box.
For us,
This is the most important place in the stadium.
This box was specially built for VIPs who come to watch the matches, and in addition to that,
for the fans.
in particular heads of state.
Given that everyone in this box has security personnel,
Additional measures have been taken to ensure the maximum safety of these individuals.
within the compound.
All their movements were planned and we made sure they did not have to cross paths with other spectators on their way to the box.
They therefore have reserved access to the stadiums and special elevator systems.
And of course,
Very specific evacuation measures have been put in place.
From the very beginning of the war,
of the stadium construction,
One of the first missions was to study the construction of this lodge in accordance with the police forces and special services.
It was under their supervision that the project was conceived and every last detail was considered.
But regardless of the quality of the dressing rooms and backstage areas,
and the technologies used to modernize these 21st-century stadiums,
the key location for a stadium,
the one around which everything must be designed
It's him.
the field.
This is where the show takes place.
where the heroes of the stadium clash.
And here,
in northern Russia,
to ensure the quality of play by the teams,
The lawn requires very special attention.
Because, given the climatic conditions and the design of the stadium,
A completely natural lawn would be far too vulnerable.
Tatiana Makarova is the agronomist in charge of the stadium's turf.
Conditions here are extremely difficult because the roof is closed and daylight and sunlight do not pass well through the roof.
The club therefore had to buy a...
additional lighting is provided on the field 24 hours a day to compensate for the lack of sunlight.
In addition,
The building is locked down.
Air circulation is difficult.
We therefore have 16 fans at our disposal which allow the grass to grow in good conditions of aeration and humidity.
But the real secret of the stadium's pitch lies elsewhere,
beneath the lawn itself,
composed of a mixture of natural and synthetic turf.
This system is fundamental.
First of all,
Using natural grass is a demand from footballers.
who prefer to play on this type of grass.
And they get injured much less often than on completely artificial turf.
So we use what is called a hybrid system.
Under the grass,
Synthetic elements stabilize the upper part.
And above,
It's natural.
This is somewhat the new way of growing grass.
The importance of the pitch to the quality of a football match and the spectacle offered to fans has given rise to a true science of turf.
It all starts at the junction between the ground and the terrain.
First of all,
Polystyrene foam with thermal insulation and waterproofing properties is placed to insulate the ground from the soil and prevent freezing.
The trenches dug in the moss then allow for the installation of channels to heat the ground and prevent mold.
Then deposit a mixture of sand and gravel which serves as the base for a synthetic substrate.
A kind of soil that will provide the grass with ideal oxygenation conditions.
Next comes a support made of synthetic filaments sewn onto a cotton fabric.
It is in turn covered with the same substrate on which the natural grass seeds will be sown.
The stadium pitch is therefore a mixed pitch in which natural grass and synthetic fibers are combined.
In my life,
this lawn,
He's a bit like a member of my family.
As soon as I arrive at the stadium,
I'm going to run right away to check the lawn and see how it's doing.
I like touching it.
And right away,
I wonder,
Does it need to be warmed up a little?
Should I add a little water to it?
She's the one who goes first.
Actually,
That's what's most valuable in this stadium.
It's a real source of pride for me and for the whole club.
Since its inauguration in April 2017,
The stadium has already hosted several international matches, including the 2018 World Cup.
The quality of the enclosure is a source of pride for the inhabitants of the city and indeed for all of Russia.
For the city,
It's a place of great importance.
It had been a very long time since a sports facility like this had been built in Saint Petersburg, or even in the entire federation.
from Russia.
For the fans,
as indeed for all the inhabitants,
It's a new center of attraction.
The arrival of a stadium like this stimulates the development of an entire neighborhood.
of the transport system.
It's certainly primarily a football stadium,
But in reality,
This stimulates many other sectors of activity.
For the players,
The atmosphere has completely changed compared to our old stadium.
The fans here are really great.
They constantly push their team.
And of course,
for the players,
This is really very important.
That motivates them even more to win.
It must also be said that there is a superb lawn.
So the game is extremely fast.
And that too,
It's very pleasant for the players to play football in these conditions.
You know,
I was born in Saint Petersburg.
I am proud to live in this city and to have such a remarkable stadium.
In my opinion,
It's the best in the world.
This stadium is truly fantastic.
The acoustics here are very good and you can hear the fans very well.
And that's very important for a team.
When you're a player and you enter the stadium,
All this support creates a very strong emotion.
Of course,
There is a feeling of pride when I step onto the pitch.
And I have a bit of a feeling of being in a grand theatre.
In Saint Petersburg,
as in Baku,
The two new stadiums have become the emblems of the city.
The Baku Olympic Stadium is the first building you see from the sky when arriving by plane.
And of course,
at night,
The enclosure is fully illuminated.
Besides,
upon arriving in town,
Many tourists call us to tell us
"We spotted your stadium from the plane and we would love to come and visit it."
That's a good sign.
This shows that we are the new trendy attraction in Baku and that we are one of the symbols of sport for our country.
The stadium is simply incredible and very impressive.
It's impossible not to notice it.
whichever route you take,
precisely because,
It is located at the intersection of all the main roads and is truly in the heart of the city.
Each seat has its own story.
as if he were remembering past events.
Sometimes,
I can even hear the voices of happy fans welcoming their favorite team.
Since their inaugurations,
The Baku Olympic Stadium and the Gazprom Arena have hosted dozens of international events.
In just a few years,
These two venues have already entered the national heritage of their country in a big way.